Guide to the Bell family papers, 1910-2004 MS 787
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Bell Family papers
1910-2004
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Bell Family
MS 787
1.25 Linear Feet 2 boxes
The collection contains correspondence, military paperwork, media, photographs, a scrapbook, and JCC and Workmen's Circle materials, which document the lives of members of the Bell family from 1910 to 2004.
Biographical / Historical
Spanning several generations, the Bell family has engaged with the Houston Jewish community at Congregation Emanu El, and through their patronage of Jewish schools, including the Workmen's Circle School, Nite Owl Program, and the Jewish Community Center Nursery. Featured by name in this collection are family members Luba Bell Wise, her daughters Minnie and Annie, and her grandson Mark Joel Birnbaum, as well as Boris "Bussie" Bell, and material donors Henrietta and Marian Bell, his wife and daughter respectively. Photo albums also feature extended family members, such as the Kapiloffs. The control folder contains the arranger's reconstructed family tree for reference.
Scope and Contents
Two boxes containing correspondence, military paperwork, media, photographs, a scrapbook, and JCC and Workmen's Circle materials document the lives of members of the Bell family from 1910 to 2004. Of particular interest are the Bell family photo albums.
This collection forms part of the South Texas Jewish Archives.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in eight series as follows:
Series I: General Series II: Jewish Community Center materials Series III: Military Series IV: Workmen's Circle Series V: Yiddish Series VI: Media Series VII: Photo Albums Series VIII: Scrapbooks
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Henrietta and Marian Bell donated the materials in July of 2018 and in June of 2019.
Index Terms
Subjects
Military; Newspapers; Jews and Jewish life; Social life and customs
Document Types
photographs; Programs (Publications); reports; Correspondence; Albums (Books)
Subjects (Persons)
Bell, Marian; Bell, Henrietta
- Series I: General
  - Family Photographs, 1935, 1962-63 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boris Bell Correspondence, 1951-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newsclippings: Boris "Bussie" Bell, 1955, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Workmen's Circle School Report Cards, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Congregation Beth Yeshurun Bulletin Celebrating B'nai Mitzvah of Marvin Stanley Weintraub (Grandson of Luba Bell Wise), 1960-02-05-1960-02-06 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jewish Community Center Nursery School Report Cards (Walter Bell), 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Piano Recital Programs (Marian Bell), 1962, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: Jewish Community Center Materials
  - JCC Brochures, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes of Snack Bar Committee Meeting, 1955-09-15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Report on the Survey of the Jewish Population in Houston, 1956-09-01 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - JCC Award for Boris Bell, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Houston Jewish Community Center Board of Directors, 1957-07 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - JCC 15th Anniversary of the Warsaw Uprisings Commemoration, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bowling Materials, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fake Subpoena to JCC Healthclub, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series III: Military
  - Military Separation Paperwork, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Air Force "Certificate of Appreciation" to Boris Bell, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series IV: Workmen's Circle
  - Workmen's Circle Branch Charter Member's List, 1947-04 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Workmen's Circle Conference Materials, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Jewish Herald Voice, 1955-09-01 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Workmen's Circle Conference Book, 1955-09 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lone Star Reporter Workmen's Circle Newsletter, 1956-11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Workmen's Circle of Houston 42nd Annual Picnic, 1957-06-23 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Workmen's Circle Tenth Anniversary Banquet, 1957-09-22 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Labor Reports Vol. XXI No. 177, 1963-05 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Ingenue's Roll-Call" Mailing List, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Workmen's Circle Mailing List, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Workmen's Circle Letter on "Camp Friendship" (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series V: Yiddish
  - Yiddish by the Bayou Newsletters, 1998-2004 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence to Henrietta Bell, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Yiddish Heritage Festival Materials, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Yiddish Vinkel Membership List, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Houston Friends of Yiddish Fund, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Yiddish Literary Society Membership List, 2004-04-22 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Yiddish Songs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Series VI: Media
  - Robinowitz Family Mac Gregor Park, 1951-06 (Box 1)
  - Waco Trip, 1959-06 (Box 1)
  - W.C. Conference O.D. Berman, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Workmen's Circle Southern District Conference Recording, 1955-09-03-1955-09-06 (Box 2)
  - David's Bar Mitzvah, 1956 (Box 2)
  - "Life with the Bells", 1959 (Box 2)
  - Gus Buck Installation Dinner, 1967-07-01 (Box 2)
  - Workmen's Circle Picnics, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Life of Marian Bell, n.d. (Box 2)
- Series VII: Photo Albums
  - Bell (and Kapiloff) Family Photo Album #4 (1/2), 1910-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bell (and Kapiloff) Family Photo Album #4 (2/2), 1910-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bell Family Photo Album (1/2), 1920s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bell Family Photo Album (2/2), 1920s - 1960s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bell Family Photo Album #1 (1/2), 1970s - 1980s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bell Family Photo Album #1 (2/2), 1970s - 1980s (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series VIII: Scrapbooks
  - Nite Owls Jewish Community Center of Houston, Beginning August 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)